Welcome,
student physicians, to the
Abnormal Cardiovascular
Examination and
Clinical Decision-Making
Lecture to prepare
you for your DPR lab.
Once again, I'm Dr.
Happel, and I have a
wonderful presentation
prepared for you all
that has some slides
in it that may be
stamped at the top that
say time for review.
So that should be a good
review from Foundations
course last year. And then at
the end of the presentation,
I also have some reference
slides for you that
have some additional
information about heart sound
libraries and things like
that. So you can go through
listening to all the heart
murmurs. So let's begin.
So here are your
session objectives,
which are part of
your CPG guide.
And let's talk about all
the different components
of the cardiovascular
examination first. so starting
with vital signs we have
the heart rate, blood
pressure, BMI, and waist
circumference so this
will also have a little
bit of review of that from
foundations then next going
to the neck for JVP as
well as carotid arteries
then the chest for the
cardiac exam and the
abdomen for the abdominal
aorta exam and then assessing
the lower extremities
and pulses and edema and
then some special tests.
So as a review, vital
scientists talk about heart
rate first. So the normal
heart rate within one
minute is 60 to 100 beats
per minute. If it is
more than 100, it's
considered tachycardia, and if
it's less than 60, it's
considered bradycardia.
And now let's talk a little
bit more in depth about
the blood pressure
classifications as it's evolved
and continued to evolve
over the past several years.
Um, so we started with the
JNC seven, which I have
here on the slide. Um, and
this is now been evolved a
few times. So let's explore
it a little bit further.
So this is the evolution
from JNC seven blood
pressure classification
guidelines to the 2017 ACC,
which is the American college
of cardiology and AHA,
which is American Heart
Association. And if you've
noticed, prehypertension
is no longer a term used.
And stage one hypertension
has kind of been moved
up a level. So if you look
at the 2017 guidelines,
stage one hypertension is
now considered systolic
of 130 to 139, or a
diastolic of 80 to 89, where
with JNC7, it was just
considered pre-hypertension.
But what I want you to know
is now that has evolved
even further. So these
are the current blood
pressure classification
guidelines that you must
know, and this is the
American Heart Association.
So your normal blood
pressure is a systolic
less than 80 and a
diastolic less, oh sorry,
a systolic less than
120 and a diastolic less
than 80. So if you notice
for it to be normal
both criteria have to be
met when it says systolic
and diastolic. So normal
again is a systolic
less than 120 and a
diastolic less than 80.
For it to be considered an
elevated blood pressure the
systolic has to be between
120 and 129 and the
diastolic has to be less than
80. So again this is where
both criteria must be met.
Once you get into stage 1
hypertension or high blood
pressure, which is in the
orange, the systolic is 130
to 139 or a diastolic of
80 to 89. So when it's or,
that means either one of
those categories would put
you in stage 1 hypertension.
So for example, if
your blood pressure
was 134 over 74 the
134 for systolic
would put you in
stage 1 hypertension
74 even though the diastolic
is less than 80 you
only need one criteria to
meet stage 1 hypertension
so you would be considered
stage 1 hypertension
at that point it's
important to know that
so whatever the highest
number is in the category,
it will always go to
that highest category.
Stage two hypertension
would be a systolic of 140
or higher or a diastolic
90 or higher. So again,
either one of those criteria
can be met. It's not both.
They added on this
hypertensive crisis, which is
very important. So it goes
a little bit further into
when that you must consult
your doctor immediately.
So this could be like your
hypertensive emergency
or urgency. So that's when
your systolic is higher
than 180 and or your
diastolic is higher than 120.
So for testing purposes,
board purposes,
clinical practice
purposes, this
is the slide you need to know.
this slide I used last
year in the foundations
about BMI and waist
circumference so I love this
slide because it really
brings BMI and waist
circumference together to
help determine increased
risk of cardiovascular
events such as
cardiovascular disease
hypertension diabetes OBDs.
So the first category just
gives you the names for
the BMI, so underweight to
extreme obesity. Then you
have your BMI categories
in the second column. And
then in your third column,
starting with obesity in
the last three classes,
obesity is now three different
classes, class one, class
two, and class three.
Then the next column over
is where the men's waist
circumference is less
than or equal to 40 inches
and the women is less
than or equal to 35
inches so these are normal
waist circumference but
if you look at someone
that is overweight and a
normal waist circumference
they are still at
increased risk to developing
cardiovascular disease
the last column is
abnormally high waist
circumference so that
overweight person that has a
normal waist circumference
uh you know has an increased
risk once that waist
circumference increases
to be abnormally high
it goes to the high
category so I do love this
slide a lot because it
helps to determine the
risk stratification for
your patients in terms of
cardiovascular disease.
So moving out of vital
signs, we go down
to the neck and
we're going to review
jugular venous pressure
and carotid pulse.
So JVP is measured greater
than three centimeters or
possibly four centimeters
above the sternal angle and
that would be considered
elevated. When you see an
elevated JVP, that can
indicate CHF, pulmonary
hypertension, tension
tricuspid stenosis
pericardial compression
or tamponade so if the jvp
falls below that you're
going to see that more
with someone that is
hypovolemic or they've had
a loss of blood so like a
hemorrhagic shock situation
now when we talk about the
carotids and we're talking
about the pulse of the carotids
the carotid upstroke may
be brisk which is normal
it could be delayed which
would suggest aortic stenosis
or bounding which could
suggest aortic insufficiency.
So if you notice I kind of
used this like red light
green light situation on
I do that a lot on the
slides so red indicate the
red font indicating that it's
abnormal and the green
indicating that it's normal.
So not only
palpating the carotid
pulse you're also
going to auscultate
the carotids to
assess for any bruise.
So now we're going
to review some of the
cardiac cycle of
systole and diastole.
So systole is when the
ventricles contract.
So the right ventricle
pumps blood into pulmonary
arteries and your
pulmonic valve opens.
The left ventricle pumps
blood into the aorta and then
the aortic valve is open. So
during systole the pulmonic
and aortic valves are open
during diastole this is
when the ventricles are
relaxed so this is when your
like semi lunar valves are
involved so the blood is
flowing from the right atrium
to the right ventricle so
your tricuspid valve is
open and from the blood flow
from the left atrium to the
left ventricle your mitral
valve is open so during
diastole which is relaxation
your tricuspid and mitral
valves are open so again this
is time for review that
little time for review stamp
knowing the areas of
auscultation, the aortic area,
pulmonic area, tricuspid,
and mitral areas, so that
you know the exact anatomical
location to auscultate.
During cardiac auscultation,
you want to auscultate
all the listening areas
for S1, S2, and S2. And
you want to use the diaphragm
of your stethoscope.
And then you can auscultate
the apex with the bell.
The diaphragm of the bell,
you know, the diaphragm
is best for detecting your
high pitch sounds such as
your s1 s2 also s4 if it's
present and most murmurs
but the bell is best for
detecting low pitch sounds
like s3 and the rumble of
a mitral stenosis murmur
so again this is time to
review know your surface
landmarks count your
interspaces identify
where are these landmarks
for yourself when you're
auscultated before
you're auscultating so
where's mid-sternal line,
the mid-clavicular line,
the anterior axillary
line, mid-axillary line.
So when we're describing
heart murmurs we talk about
the timing and duration
and so this is again just a
little bit of a review and
then when you get to the
valvular heart disease lecture
that I do in this course
as well I'm going to go a
little bit further detail.
So you want to identify and
describe any murmurs that
you hear. So are the murmurs
systolic or diastolic.
So a good tip to know in
timing if it's a systolic
murmur or a diastolic murmur
is you're going to palpate
the carotid upstroke,
which it occurs in systole,
as you're auscultating the
heart. So if the murmur
coincides with the carotid
upstroke, it's systolic.
Now the duration of the
murmur, it could be early
systolic, mid-systolic,
late-systolic, or
holosystolic, meaning
throughout the entire systole.
Or it could be early diastolic,
mid-diastolic, or
late diastolic.
So when you're describing
the heart murmurs, we also
think about the shape
of the murmur as you're
auscultating. So is it a
crescendo where it gets louder,
a decrescendo as it gets
softer, or both where you
get a crescendo and then
a decrescendo, which is
called a diamond shaped. So
an example of a crescendo
decrescendo systolic
murmur is aortic stenosis.
An example of a
holosystolic murmur is
mitral regurgitation.
So I have these little
pictures here. These
are from Bates. It
also should be a review
from Foundations.
And then when you're
describing the
heart murmurs, you
also want to describe
the quality of the
murmur, the pitch.
So the quality could be
harsh, musical, soft, blowing,
rumbling. The pitch could
be high, medium, or low.
So examples,
and this is what
you'll see like on
board exams or any
sort of exam items,
they'll describe to you
what the murmur sounds like
and where you hear it best,
and you should be able
to determine based on
that information what type
of murmur it is. So for
example, a harsh two out
of six medium pitched
holosystolic murmur best
appreciated at the apex
would be your mitral regurge.
Another example is a soft
blowing three out of six
decrescendo diastolic murmur
best heard at the lower left
sternal border. And that
could be aortic regurge. So
again, we're going to go
through all murmurs in the
valdeal heart disease lecture,
playing, playing them,
talking about cases. Where
do you see it best? Where
do you hear it best? So even
before you would hear the
sound, you already have an
idea of what murmur it is.
So you also need
to describe the
intensity or the
grades of the murmur.
So grade one is very
faint. Grade two is quiet.
Grade three is moderately
loud. Those are usually
ones that as a medical
student, you may hear
first starting at grade
three, unless you have
super auscultative powers,
which is fantastic.
Um, so grade four, five,
and six, not only are
loud or very loud, but they'll
have a palpable thrill.
So as you're palpating
the precordium on the
chest, you can feel a
thrill or like a pulsation.
So what's your approach
to diagnosing heart
murmurs, timing, and
duration? Here's a nice
little, I like this
little algorithm. Um,
so systolic versus
diastolic, you know, is a
crescendo decrescendo
you think of a stenosis
so it could be aortic
or pulmonic or pulmonary
if it's holosystolic
it's usually a
regurgitation so that could
be mitral or tricuspid
um early diastolic or
decrescendo could be a
regurg murmur regurgitation
murmur aortic or pulmonary
if it's mid late uh
diastolic you think of
more of a stenosis like
a mitral or a tricuspid
if you have a continuous
murmur so you have
systolic and diastolic
murmur you want to think
about pda or patent ductus
arteriosus so this is
a good way of kind of
looking at an algorithm
to help you diagnose murmurs
so it'd be a good precursor
for you before you get
to the valvular heart
disease lecture then you
also want to assess the point
of maximal impulse of the
PMI so the PMI is a tapping
it's normal if it's sustained
it could indicate LVH
which could indicate an
underlying hypertension or
aortic stenosis and if it's
diffuse you want to think
more like a dilated ventricle
so either like a CHF
or cardiomyopathy so when
it comes to PMI location
amplitude duration and
diameter if it's less than 2
.5 centimeters it's normal
in pregnancy the PMI may be
displaced up and to the
left because the baby the
growing baby may displace it
in RVH or right ventricular
hypertrophy it may displace
the PMI to the right
in LVH or cardiomegaly
it may displace your
PMI laterally or more
to the left more towards
that anterior axillary
line and with pressure
overloaded at the left
ventricle so either
aortic stenosis, or if
you have volume overload
at the left ventricle,
which is like a mitral
regurgitation, that could
indicate an increased
amplitude. So these are all
just like good little reminders
of where you palpate that
PMI, what does it feel
like, and what could be
going on with the patient.
Really great physical
exam maneuver.
Then when you get to the
abdomen, you want to be
able to palpate the
abdominal aorta. So if that
abdominal aorta is less
than three centimeters, it's
normal. If it's greater
than three centimeters,
you want to consider getting
further imaging about
and assessing for that
abdominal aortic aneurysm.
When you're examining
the lower extremities and
checking for edema, so no
pitting edema, one plus
is mild two plus is moderate
three plus is moderately
severe and four plus
is severe okay so you
basically you want to
indent your thumb let it go
and then see how rapidly
that edema improves now
a special test for if you
could if you're worried about
peripheral artery disease
in your patients is the
ankle brachial index or
abi and it's a specific and
sensitive metric for the
diagnosis of PAD or peripheral
arterial disease. It's been
shown to predict mortality
and adverse cardiovascular
events independent of
traditional cardiovascular
risk factors. So the major
cardiovascular societies advise
measuring an ABI in every
smoker over the age of 50,
every diabetic over 50, and
all patients over the age
of 70. and it's calculated
by measuring the systolic
blood pressure at the ankle
and that is over or divided by
your systolic
pressure at the arm.
So if you look at this
nice little table,
ABI value of 1 to 1.4 is normal
and ABI of 0.9 to
1 is acceptable.
So in those two
cases, you do not have
to refer to a
vascular specialist.
As you go down the table,
0.8 to 0.9 can indicate
some arterial disease.
You want to treat any risk
factors, hypertension,
dyslipidemia, diabetes,
smoking.
0.5 to 0.8 is moderate
arterial disease and less
than 0.5 is severe
arterial disease. In both
those categories, you
really want to consider
referring your patient
to a vascular specialist.
so clinical problem solving
we're going to go through
some cardiovascular complaints
and then I'm going to
run through a case with you
to help show you how your
problem clinical decision
making is helping you
through the case so you know
what's going on with the
patient what's your differential
what are you going to
ask for your review of
systems what are you going to
ask for um your actual history
taking including family
history what physical
exam maneuvers will you do
to help you determine what
is the most likely diagnosis
so first let's just go
through some cardiovascular
complaints so again this
is time for review this was
all in Bates and this should
be a review from foundations
so chest pain let's talk
about the symptom of
chest pain you always
want to consider your life
-threatening conditions angina
myocardial infarction dissecting
aortic aneurysm, pulmonary
embolism. And remember
that the etiology may not
be cardiac. So it could
be pulmonary, it could be GI,
it could be musculoskeletal.
So don't pigeonhole your
differential. When you
think of chest pain, the
first thing you should think
of is everything possible
that can cause chest pain.
But always consider the
life-threatening diagnoses.
So where is the chest
pain? Is it left
-sided? What does it
feel like? So is it a
pressure? Is it a tightness?
Is it a sharp pain?
Does it radiate?
Where does it radiate?
Does it feel like an elephant
sitting on your chest?
You know, is there
associated shortness of
breath? Does the pain
radiate to the jaw?
Is there associated
nausea and vomiting?
Any associated diaphoresis?
So these will all
help to determine this
is a clear cardiac
etiology if any of these
symptoms are there.
Some atypical
presentation and symptoms
with chest pain, you
want to consider your
patient population.
So if you have women,
geriatrics, or diabetics,
they can have a
little bit atypical
presentation of cardiac etiology
chest pain. They
might have upper back
pain, jaw pain, arm pain,
typically left-sided,
shortness of breath,
paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea,
nausea, vomiting,
fatigue. And especially in
women, we see that a lot
is they're just tired,
they have no
energy, and they're
getting like mild
dyspnea on exertion.
Now let's talk about the
symptom of palpitations.
So it's really like that
unpleasant awareness of
your heartbeat some people
describe it as skipping
racing fluttering pounding
they feel their heart
stops and then restarts you
know so these are all ways
patients may describe
what a palpitation feels
like so cardiac etiologies
could be an arrhythmia or
a forceful cardiac
contraction but common non
-cardiac etiologies could be
anxiety, hyperthyroidism.
Now let's talk
about the symptom of
shortness of breath.
So there's different
types. There's
dyspnea, orthopnea,
and Parkinson's nocturnal
dyspnea. So dyspnea is
that uncomfortable awareness
of breathing that's
inappropriate to a given
level of exertion. Like I'm
short of breath. I'm
aware that I'm breathing a
little abnormally that's
not really you know
appropriate to me sitting
here listening to a lecture.
Orthopnea is dyspnea that
occurs when the patient's
lying down and it improves
when they're sitting up.
And then paroxysmal
nocturnal dyspnea is
episodes of sudden
dyspnea and orthopnea
that awakens the
patient from sleep.
Now let's talk about the
symptom of lower extremity
edema. So this is the
accumulation of that excess
fluid in the extravascular
interstitial space.
And the interstitial tissue
can absorb liters of fluid.
So things that you can
ask your patient during
your interview as you're
gathering a history is
like, have you noticed
any swelling? Have you
noticed where it occurs?
Is it just the ankles?
Is it just the lower
legs? Does it go all the
way up to the knee? Is
it one-sided, both-sided?
Is it worse in the
morning or at night.
And then just looking at
some cardiovascular risks
from the patient's history.
So is there any past medical
history of hypertension,
diabetes, or dyslipidemia?
I call that the unhappy triad
of cardiovascular disease.
Past history, did
they have any past
cardiac surgeries?
Do they have a stent?
Did they have a valve
replaced or repaired?
when you think of
medications and allergies
if they do have any
past medical history
of cardiovascular
risk are they taking
medicine are they
compliant with the medicine
family history any
cardiovascular disease
and what age they were
diagnosed with the
cardiovascular disease
think of social
history any smoking so
have you ever smoked
and also are you actively
smoking any other drug use
previous or active so you
really have to you know
decipher not just right now
right here in the office do
they smoke or do drugs
right but also in the past
have they ever uh physical
inactivity and unhealthy
diet those are also important
components of the social
history and even when it
comes to unhealthy diet
consider caffeine overuse so
maybe not just coffee coffee
or could be red bull it
could be monster it could
be caffeine supplements
it could be uh supplements
that have things that are
a caffeine derivative but
they have such a crazy name
patients may not know that
and then looking
at the vital signs
once you're doing
your physical exam
looking at the weight
the BMI and the waist
circumference so especially
the central adiposity and
obesity increases the risk
of cardiovascular disease
so this is the end of
the first part we're
going to pick up the
second part of the
lecture on going
through a case together